Alvin O. Hurst papers, 1946-1972
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Alvin O. Hurst papers, 1946-1972
MS 424
Alvin O. Hurst
Papers, 1946-1972 (bulk 1952-1969). This collection is comprised of the papers of landscape architect Alvin O. Hurst. Items include business files and writings. The bulk of the material consists of business records including correspondence, plans, reports and drawings, relating to various projects from Mr. Hurst’s career as a landscape architect for federal and state agencies primarily in the southwestern United States.
3.0 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Alvin O. Hurst was born in 1919 in Illinois. He began college at the University of Illinois- Urbana in 1939. From 1942 to1945, Mr. Hurst served in the United States Army Air Corps as a pilot. After World War II, Mr. Hurst returned to the University of Illinois- Urbana and completed his Bachelor of Arts degree in landscape architecture in 1948. After graduation he joined the staff of the National Park Service. Mr. Hurst worked on several projects and surveys in the Eastern United States including the Natchez Trace Parkway in Tupelo, Mississippi and the New England Interagency Committee in Boston, Massachusetts.
In1955, Mr. Hurst transferred to Yuma, Arizona to become the supervisory park landscape architect in charge of the Lower Colorado River Survey. From 1957 to 1959 Mr. Hurst served as secretary of the Recreation Subcommittee of the Pacific Southwest Inter-agency Committee. In 1958 Mr. Hurst became a recreation planner in charge of a portion of the National Park Service’s National Recreation Plan based in New Mexico.
In 1962 he took a temporary assignment as a planning consultant to the Secretary of the Interior's Land Use Advisory Committee at the Lower Colorado River Land Use Office in Yuma, Arizona where he wrote the Lower Colorado River Land Use Plan which was a landmark publication in land-use planning and was approved by Secretary of the Interior, Stewart Udall. He briefly left the Southwest from 1963 to 1964 to work as a Recreation Resources Planner in Atlanta, Georgia. In 1964 he returned permanently to the Lower Colorado River Land Use Office in Yuma, Arizona. Alvin Hurst was recognized for his ability to accommodate a wide variety of recreational activities into recreational spaces without an excessive amount of damage to the environment. He died in Yuma in 1974.
Organization
This collection is organized into 2 series
Series 1: Business Files, 1946-1972
Series 2: Writings, 1962
Scope and Content Note
Papers, 1946-1972 (bulk 1952-1969). This collection contains the papers of Alvin O. Hurst relating to his career in landscape architecture in the southwestern United States. The bulk of the material includes business records that document Mr. Hurst’s career working with the National Park Service. The majority of the materials relate to Mr. Hurst’s work at the Lower Colorado River Land Use Office in Yuma, Arizona. Also included are writings which consist of short essays by Mr. Hurst concerning different topics in landscape architecture.
Access Terms
Hurst, Alvin- Archives.
United States. National Park Service.
United States. Lower Colorado River Land Use Office.
Lower Colorado River Land Use Advisory Committee.
Pacific Southwest Inter-agency Committee.
American Society of Landscape Architects.
Landscape architecture.
Recreation--Planning.
Recreation--Planning--United States.
Container List
- Series 1: Business Files 1946-1972
  Arrangement: Alphabetical. This series contains business records pertaining to Alvin O. Hurst’s career as a landscape architect including correspondence with professional organizations, reports, project files, speeches and committee files.
  - American Society of Landscape Architects. 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Society of Landscape Architects- Annual Meeting. 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Society of Landscape Architects- Correspondence. 1 1962-196363 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Arizona Association of Landscape Architects- Symposium. 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - California Division of Beaches and Parks. 1952-1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - California Fish and Game. 1952-1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - California Fish and Game. 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Colorado River Channelization Project. 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence. 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence. 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence. 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence. 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence- Arizona Game and Fish. 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence- Fish and Wildlife Service (Imperial Refuge). 1955-1958 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence- Fish and Wildlife Service (Lake Havasu Refuge). 1955-1958 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Havasu Lake National Wildlife Refuge Plan. 1957 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - International Federation of Landscape Architects- Meeting. 1958 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Laguna Unit Plan. 1956 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Louisiana Art Commission. 1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Lower Colorado River District Office- Organization Structure. 1972 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Lower Colorado River Land Use Advisory Committee. 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Lower Colorado River Land Use Office- Budget and Compendium. 1965 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Lower Colorado River Land Use Office- Reports. 1946-1958 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Lower Colorado River Land Use Office- Reports. 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Lower Colorado River Land Use Office- Reports. 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Lower Colorado River Land Use Office- Reports. 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Lower Colorado River Land Use Office- Workshops. 1962 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Lower Colorado River Land Use Plan. 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Lower Colorado River Parkway. 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Lower Colorado River Recreation Road System Plan. 1963-1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Lower Colorado River Recreation Road System Plan. 1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Lower Colorado River Survey: A Recreation Land Use Plan. 1958 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - National Recreation Plan. Undated, 1958-1973 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Old Custom House Project. 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Pacific Southwest Inter-Agency Committee- Recreation Subcommittee. 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Pacific Southwest Inter-Agency Committee- Recreation Subcommittee. 1961 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Pacific Southwest Inter-Agency Committee- Recreation Subcommittee. 1962 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Pacific Southwest Inter-Agency Committee- Recreation Subcommittee. 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Parker Area Plan. 1956 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Parker Area Plan- Correspondence. 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Parker Division Channelization. 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Personnel. 1952-1966 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Speeches. 1956-1970 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - State Highway Engineer- Arizona and California. 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Topock Gorge Channelization. 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Yuma Division Channelization. 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Yuma Units- Yuma North and South. 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Series 2: Writings 1962
  Arrangement: Alphabetical. This series contains a collection of essays entitled “Outcroppings” by Alvin O. Hurst that he intended to have published in Landscape Architect.
  - Outcroppings I- On Land Use Planning. 1962 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Outcroppings II- On Recreation- Some Influences. 1962 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Outcroppings III- On Recreation- Some Factors. 1962 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Outcroppings IV- On Society- Some Reflections. 1962 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Outcroppings V- On Space and Planning. 1962 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Outcroppings VI- On Planning- Some Considerations. 1962 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Outcroppings VII- On Forcasting- Some Ruminations. 1962 (Box 3, Folder 14)